<entry identifier="p080v_a1">
<folio number="080v"
  url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f166.image"/>


<heading>Founders of small <material>tin</material> work</heading>

<block>
  They usually cast from soft <material>solder</material> the things that should not become hollow, because hollow works require fine and <material>soft tin</material>. However, these things would not otherwise lose their coat or become hollow if they are mixed or include <material>glass tin</material>  in them, just like they mix a little <sup><material>glass tin</material></sup> in the <material>soft tin</material>. They carve their work on <material>stones</material> of which the sharpening stones or barber's files are made. These are found in great flakes near the <place>mountains</place>, and resemble <material>slate</material>. They are found in three colors: one reddish, that is not as perfect as the others because it does not sustain heat ; <sup>another</sup> one  is the color of dark <material>slate</material>, and the other is whitish. When they work a relief, first they print it on <material>carton</material>, which is one finger thick, to serve as a pattern. After planing their <material>stones</material> and rubbing them together , they use a <tool>compass</tool> or <tool>little iron tools</tool> to carve their figures. They make their molds with three or four <material>stones</material>, to make a circle or a square with the <material>stones</material> which join perfectly because the <material>stones</material> are of equal size. Before casting, they rub the mould over with <material>tallow</material>, and it <sup>the mould</sup> absorbs it quickly because it is hot. Then, having <sup>put</sup> fine powder of <material>quicklime</material> into a <tool>cloth</tool>, they rub the mould using pounce in beating the <material>linen</material> on top, then blow it a little on top; this prevents bubbles <sup>from forming</sup>. The main thing is to make some vents. If the work is big, they do as it is shown <sup>on the picture</sup>. They make a hole in the <m>medal</m>, somewhere where it is least visible, and with a bit they pierce the mold on the side of the <material>medal</material>.
</block>

<figure identifier="fig_p080r_1"
  url="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5VktqeFlScTAyczQ"/>

<block>And if they want their work to last, they pierce <sup>it</sup> somewhere and fit in a piece of <material>cork</material>. <material>Lead</material> or <material>tin</material> will not damage it. </block>

</entry>
