<entry identifier="p106r_a2">
<folio
number="106r"
url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f217.image"/>

<heading>Making gold run for casting</heading>

<block>Because <material>gold</material> cools down very quickly, you have to give it a mixture when it is well melted that will keep the heat. <material>Sublimate</material> softens it nicely. But, since it vanishes into <material>smoke</material>, it won't aid you for very long. Therefore mix this mixture into it when you want to cast it: of <material>sal ammoniac</material>, the best <material>verdigris</material> that you can find, a bit of <material>borax</material> and some <material>saltpeter</material>. And this, held over the heat, will become neat. The <material>saltpeter</material> makes it clear and heats it. But the key thing in this mixture is the <material>verdigris</material>, which has to be good. This mixture softens your <material>gold</material> so much that it becomes as tractable as <material>lead</material>, even if it is good <material>gold</material>.</block>

<!-- Does everything that follows still belong to the 'Making gold run for casting' entry?-->

<block>For <material>sand</material> for molding <material>flowers</material> and <material>leaves</material> &amp; other delicate things, mix in <material>raw plaster</material>, <material>crushed brick</material> and <material>stone alum</material>.</block>

<block>To moisten <material>sand</material>, <material>spirits</material> are excellent because it makes <material>sand</material> fine and leaves in a vapor when you reheat your <tool>box frame</tool>.</block>

<block><material>Dilute sal ammoniac</material> is very good, is excellent for moistening <material>sand</material>, but for lots of <material>water</material> you only need a little bit of <material>sal ammoniac</material>.</block>

<block>A raw lump of <material>metal</material>, if you don't have <material>crocum ferri</material>, is good for <material>gold</material>.</block>

<block>The <animal>snakes</animal> and the <animal>lizards</animal> you wish to mold should not be kept for a long time, because if they are alive, they will waste away, and if they are dead, they will decay.</block>

<block><material>Plaster of Paris</material> is as hard as <material>stone</material> and very good. When you want to choose some for your <material>sand</material>, take the rawest and the hardest that is possible for you &amp; that does not make any powder. Transparent <material>[plaster]</material> and that which makes powder in giving way is that which is not good for this work. A sign of that which is near perfect is that it is hard &amp; makes shining grains that look almost like <material>sugar</material>. Finally, to mix it into the <material>sand</material> to cast <material>gold</material>, it has to be put in the fire twice, &amp; reheated twice.</block>

<margin-block position="left-top" purpose="making">
When <material>gold</material> is really pure, it is so dry that it can just barely endure a <tool>hammer</tool>. But this mixture softens it like <material>lead</material>.
</margin-block>
</entry>
