<entry identifier="p108r_a1">
<folio
start="108r"
end="108v"
url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f221.image"
url2="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f222.image"/>

<heading>Spalt</heading>
<block purpose="making">
<material>Spalt</material> is white like <material>cooked plaster</material> and one can find it in mounds and <material>stones</material> made in long stairs and long veins. It is very soft such that with a fingernail and it makes a powder like that of our <material>chalk from Champagne</material>. And because everything which is provided from the earth is mixed with some other substance, to purify it [the spalt], one boils it with somewhat large <material>gemstones</material> then tempers it with <material>essence of sal ammoniac</material>. One puts [a lump of it] <unit>the size of a walnut</unit> in a large <tool>bottle</tool> of <material>water</material> and that way one tempers it &amp; reducing it into small balls, [one] purges it of impurities [by] then putting it on to cook cleanly in a <tool>vessel of earth[enware]</tool> in a <tool>furnace</tool> like those in which <tool>pots</tool> [are made] and one leaves it there to the point at which <tool>pots</tool> would be fired. After one tempers it more with <material>essence of sal ammoniac</material> &amp; boiling it very strongly and emptying the <material>murky water</material> &amp; putting it in a separate <tool>vessel</tool> straight after put back the same <material>water</material> over it &amp; one boils &amp; one puts back the <material>murky water</material> again with the other. And one does this therefore until that which is there has passed away. In this way one purges and purifies and makes it a very fine and malleable [matter]. After one has taken away the <material>water</material> by tilting [it] or with a <tool>sponge</tool>, one takes the residue and dries it. Then moistening it with the aforementioned <material>water</material> the way one did with the other <material>sand</material>, one uses it in a <tool>frame</tool> or if it shrinks [this] is a sign that it is not fired enough &amp; needs to be fired more. This one is proper for molding all <material>metal</material> and especially <material>gold</material> and <material>silver</material> and the more it is used the better it is. One should put <material>alum</material> which you have cast of <material>lead</material> or <material>tin</material> separately because it makes <material>gold</material>. sour if you cast it there.
</block>
</entry>
