<entry identifier="p140v_3">
    <folio number="140v" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f286.item.r="/>



        <heading>Casting of lead and tin in plaster</heading>

       <!-- <related-block> --> 
            <block purpose="making"> If you want to cast any <keyword>flat medal</keyword> or any
                    <keyword>animal</keyword> that is not very heavy, and that must not be burnt
                inside the mold, you can indeed cast in <material>mixed plaster</material> &amp;
                    <material>brique</material>, as above; and not in plaster alone, because it
                contracts too much feeling an ardent fire if it is not so mixed. But, with the
                brick, it holds well. However, take heed to dry out your mold at length &amp; on a
                slow fire &amp; with patience, because there is no need to reheat it. But when your
                work is of <keyword>flowers</keyword> or other things that want their mold to be
                reheated &amp; set ablaze, mix the plaster with stone alum &amp; even with crocum. I
                have molded in very neat <material>plaster &amp; brick</material> &amp; it has
                sustained several castings. </block>

            <block position="left-middle" purpose="making"> I tried both plaster &amp; brick alone
                and molded en <material>noyau</material> with like the others. My mold was very
                clean, <activity>having lightly oiled &amp; rubbed my medal with spirits</activity>.
                I made my casting wide at the entrance, narrowing it as it goes along until it
                reaches the medal which is very thin. I notched the casting which embraced the medal
                well. I dried the mold out well on a slow fire &amp; finally, I heated it well
                without turning it red. I let it cool in such a way that I could hold my finger to
                it without burning myself. I made a line of 4 ℥ of <material>tin</material>, &amp;
                ix deniers of <material>lead</material>. I cast it <keyword>red</keyword>, and it
                was quite good and beautiful. Afterwards I put xii deniers of lead on top of 4 ℥ of
                tin. It is very good &amp; beautiful. </block>

            <block position="left-bottom"> When there is nothing to burn in the mold, it is not
                necessary to reheat it for lead and tin. But for flowers and other things that must
                be burned, it is. </block>
       <!--  </related-block>  -->

    
</entry>
