<entry identifier="p141r_1">
    <folio number="141r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f287.image"/>

    <heading>
        <activity>Casting a crayfish</activity>
    </heading>

    <block purpose="making"> The <keyword>crayfish</keyword> is one of the most fantastical to cast,
        but also <activity>provides an example for casting other difficult things</activity>. You
        can distinguish males and female by the eggs that the females carry, and by the four little
        white back legs that males have in their tails after behind main eight legs. It is good to
        dry them out a bit so that the bumps come out more hard and beautiful, because none of what
        is made of shell shrinks. It is true that should you dry the little inside legs for too
        long, they become diminished and have no body. If they are too dry, the flesh separates from
        the scales. Be sure then to maintain the mean. They have certain hairs between the legs and
        at the end of the tail. And because all hair is difficult to cast, because it gets mixed up
        in the sand and does not release, you can burn it by putting a <tool>hot iron</tool> on the
        crayfish so that it the hair cannot be seen. As for <keyword>animals</keyword> that have
        hair or feathers, you must grease the hair with <material>wheat oil</material>, which is
        very dry and which will make the hair lay flat and straight. In this way, you will have form
        of your animal and you will have the hair. Should it the hair be wavy, it can be repaired.
        If your crayfish has eggs, which are delicate, and which will be difficult to take out of
        the mold without breaking, you would do better to make the first cast with the crayfish on
        its belly and eggs. In this way, you will open the mold with it the crayfish on its back,
        which will be hard and easy to manipulate. And the belly and the eggs will remain in the
        mold. And rather than opening your mold for the second time, you will have to burn it with
        them in it. This way, it will open easily, and what has been burned will come away cleanly.
        In this way, the second casting, which is done on the first one that has successfully taken
        hold, separates easily from the first, after having been refired. This is a singular secret
        for similar moldings. </block>

    <block position="left-top" purpose="making"> The casting is made by the very thin tail. </block>

    <block position="top" purpose="advice"> If some little thing is missing, you can reattach it or
        else fill it with <material>goldsmith's cement</material>. </block>

    <block position="left-top" purpose="advice"> Do not forget to rub with
            <material>spirits</material> before you mold. </block>

    <block position="left-top" purpose="making">
        <keyword>Stag beetles, crayfish and crabs</keyword> are molded in the same way. </block>

    <block position="left-middle" purpose="advice"> If your crayfish has no eggs, mold the back on
        top and the belly on the bottom. You can give it some. </block>

    <block position="left-middle" purpose="advice"> It the crayfish can be molded hollow for the
        body, but not for the legs. And for a good result, take note that the crayfish is rather
        fantastical to mold hollow, this ought to be reserved for turtles. </block>

    <block position="left-bottom" purpose="making"> When you open your mold, you will find the
        crayfish has white bones, but they will not be powder. And without opening it, the mercury
        will not have affected the process. </block>

    <block position="bottom" purpose="making"> Apply very light <keyword>oil colors</keyword>. </block>

    <block position="bottom" purpose="making"> To paint it, boil it with wine and a bit of
            <material>salt</material> so that they become very red and use this as a model. Paint
        the back with <keyword>vermillion mixed with laquer</keyword>, and the sides and the
        underside of the belly and the legs with <keyword>vermillion and yellow ochre and
            white</keyword>. </block>



    <folio number="141v" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f288.image"/>

    <block purpose="making"> Let your crayfish dry a little in the sun, by itself. If it has spawns,
        they will shrink while drying, and be all the more beautiful for it. Make your paste out of
        yellow <material>potter's earth</material>, just like for the other representations. Lay
        your crayfish on it, the back side down, and the other parts which are more tricky to mold
        -- legs, belly, eggs - side up. Drive in the back side in the clay paste up to the legs,
        which is about the half part of the crayfish's body. Fix the body with a pointy iron thread
        in the middle and, if you feel you need it, you can also drive another one at the edge of
        the tail. And in order that the big legs be lower than the head, which is lower because it
        is linked from below, add a little <material>clay</material> under the head. Then add a bit
        of <material>clay</material> under the jacket in order to raise it. Hide the feelers under
        the clay and under the crusher claws, then arrange it as you like. Stretch out the walking
        legs to the joints, and for the first cast, bend the second part of the walking legs. Fix
        the joints of the legs with wax and a warm wire so they will not move. If you want to mould
        something fancier, fix the end of one walking legs on the body or on a crusher claw , using
        the same <material>wax</material>. If the female has spawns, bent half the tail over the
        spawns, and keep the shape by fixing the tail with a wire. Be sure that you will be able to
        clean this part. Finally <activity>rub your crayfish with spirits, and cast your
            sand</activity>. Once the sand is hardened, uncover the back side, the head, the eyes,
        and the small legs close to the crusher claws, and the walking legs all along. One must
        uncover these parts as much as possible. Then bend and cover the spawns again. The other
        animals </block>

    <block position="left-top" purpose="making"> Fix what may raise the two padded edges on each
        side of the mouth with melted wax under them. </block>
    
    <block position="left-middle">
        <image identifier="fig_p141v_1"
            url="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5R0NIbHoyNTNQRlk"/>
   </block>
    <!-- ![fig_p141v_1] (https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5R0NIbHoyNTNQRlk)
-->

    <block position="left-middle" purpose="making"> Uncover as many parts as possible, but be sure
        the channels you make are well stripped. </block>

    <block position="left-middle" purpose="making"> Incline your mould to the thickest side of the
        animal. </block>

    <block position="left-bottom" purpose="making"> To paint the crayfish, one paints the middle of
        the back with <keyword>vermilion, mixed with a bit of lacquer</keyword>. The sides, the
        belly, and below the legs with a mixture made of <keyword>vermilion, ceruse, and a bit of
            yellow ochre</keyword>. As with all things, always keep the real one in front of you in
        order to copy it as realistically as possible. </block>
    <block position="left-bottom" purpose="making"> Lay the feelers on the crusher claws, or solder
        this part with a wire made of bleached brass. </block>
    <block position="bottom" purpose="making"> When you arrange the legs, be sure that they do not
        get over the belly, and that they are well set against the belly otherwise [illegible] </block>



    <folio number="142r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f289.image"/>
 
    <block purpose="making"> are not so uncovered. But since crayfish are troublesome to burn &amp;
        clean, you have to uncover them as much as you can, even the little legs just until the
        tips, because they are troublesome &amp; if, in order to not alter them, you have to take
        them out, you could break something of the mold. Having uncovered it with the point of a
            <tool>knife</tool>, like an <tool>engraving stick</tool> or another fitting thing, clean
        off the <material>sand</material> at the joints &amp; elsewhere with your little brush
        really very scrupulously. And if something is loosed from the <keyword>crayfish</keyword>,
        attach it with <material>wax</material>, as is discussed. And also attach the horns this
        way. And also do the casting the length of the extremes of the little legs with wax. And
        refill the holes that have been made with the needles of <material>iron wire</material> with
        it. And everything being quite clean &amp; having uncovered more than half of it, oil your
        mold after having soaked the back side in water, &amp; do not forget to oil all the fine
        parts that are between the legs and the little beaks; then rub the crayfish with spirits.
        And do your second casting after having made the first mold even, so that the cramp-irons
        join better. Your mold must be larger on the side with the impression than on the back. Do
        not open your mold after the second casting, so that it not become clayed &amp; reheated
        &amp; that which is inside not be burned. Do not forget to mix crocum throughout your sand
        when you mold the crayfish, because you must really reheat it &amp; the
            <material>crocum</material> withstands this marvelously. <activity>To mold a crab &amp;
            to <activity/>mold a crayfish are exactly the same</activity>. When you have uncovered
        your crayfish on one side do not delay at all before doing the second casting, because
        crayfish dry out. It is not enough to uncover the crayfish such that you see the whole half
        the half you uncover, but take heed that your mold, even when you are uncovering, be good
        and stripped, because if the crayfish gets well burnt, you will not be able to open your
        mold without breaking it. </block>

    <block position="top" purpose="making"> Restore it with a <tool>pen knife, little chisels, or
            engraving sticks</tool>. </block>

    <block position="left-top" purpose="making"> As you see here, but a wax casting all around &amp;
        at the end of the tail, where you will do the principal casting, two or three more. 
        <image identifier="fig_p142r_1"
            url="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5Qkh2MDhvUkFnUW8"/>
    
    </block>

 

    <!--
![fig_p142r_1] (https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5Qkh2MDhvUkFnUW8)
-->

    <block position="left-middle" purpose="making"> Make the casting with <material>candle
            wax</material> shaped in a thread like a large packthread, the whole length from the end
        of the claws to the extremity of the tail. If there is also some claw end or other part that
        is extended past the rank of the others or is raised up higher or turned up all alone, make
        a wax casting for it from its end just barely not joined to the body or to one of the large
        claws or to some other place where lots of metal will be wedged in. </block>

    <block position="left-bottom" purpose="making"> Having uncovered it, attach &amp; secure the two
        little bearded horns of the crayfish, and anything else that is not secured, with wax. </block>



</entry>
